A Guide to the Lewis W. Hackett Papers FA043
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lewis W. Hackett papers
1875-1962
1689-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hackett, Lewis Wendell
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board
FA043
20.7 Cubic Feet 30 document cases
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
Lewis Wendell Hackett was born in Benicia, California, on December 14, 1884. He received an A.B. degree from Harvard University in 1905 and an M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1912. He had become interested in public health administration and was appointed Assistant in Preventive Medicine and Hygiene at the university. During the following year, he organized and taught a laboratory and field course in hygiene. In 1913, he was granted the first Dr.P.H. degree given at Harvard Medical School. He was promoted to Instructor in Preventive Medicine and Hygiene, and in this capacity he helped to organize the first school for public health officers in the United States.
In 1914, Dr. Hackett was recruited for the field staff of the newly organized International Health Board of the Rockefeller Foundation. His next 35 years were spent in 17 foreign countries investigating and combating hookworm disease and malaria and promoting public health. His first assignment was to conduct hookworm control demonstrations in Panama, British Honduras, and Guatemala. He also took charge of the Brazilian program in 1916 and expanded the work to include malaria control and the development of public health organizations.
The second major period of Dr. Hackett's employment began in 1924 when he took charge of the International Health Board project in Italy, where malaria was active in 38 of the 69 provinces. Control demonstrations were first organized in Sardinia. His use of Paris green as a larvacide was effective and was extended to other areas. He was instrumental in establishing a Central Malaria Experiment Station in Rome for the study of the anopheline mosquito. Of the six identified varieties of the maculipennis complex, two were confirmed as significant in the spread of malaria. In 1936, Dr. Hackett set up an Albanian field station for similar anopheline research. His book, "Malaria in Europe," published in 1937, summarized his studies to date. In 1939, his field laboratory work was extended to the Nile delta in Egypt. The Foundation closed its Rome office in 1940, when Italy entered the Second World War.
The remaining nine years of Dr. Hackett's service were spent as Director of the Rio de la Plata and Andean regional office in Buenos Aires, Argentina, where he administered programs in Argentina, Chile, Ecuador, Bolivia, Peru, and Uruguay. He found a generally unpromising situation, with the medical profession dominated by politics and the public health concept erroneous or non-existent. The war, lack of qualified personnel, and political instability combined to impede progress. A health center in Chile and nursing schools in Ecuador and Peru were the most solid achievements. The rise of a totalitarian government in Argentina curbed International Health Division activities there, and the Buenos Aires office was closed in September 1949.
At his retirement in December 1949, Dr. Hackett was an Associate Director of the IHD. He settled in Berkeley, where he became Visiting Professor of Public Health at the University of California and Editor-in-Chief of the "American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene." He was a member of many scientific and learned societies and served on commissions of the League of Nations and World Health Organization. Among his many honors were decorations from the governments of Italy, Chile, Bolivia, and Ecuador. His many published articles included a contribution to the "Encyclopedia Britannica" on tropical medicine, and at his death on April 28, 1962, he was working on another book, a history of the International Health Division. Much of his material was subsequently included in Greer Williams' "The Plague Killers."
Scope and Contents note
Important subjects in this collection are Argentina - Instituto de Bacteriologia, Buenos Aires; Argentina - nursing school, Rosario; Argentina - political situation, especially as it affected universities; Chile - Quinta Normal Health Center; disease control - malaria, especially in the Lurin Valley, Peru; disease control - yellow fever, especially in Bolivia and Peru; Ecuador - National Institute of Hygiene, Guayaquil; epidemiology - general; epidemiology - malaria; epidemiology - yellow fever; insecticides - Paris green, DDT and others; Peru - Ica Health Center; public health - administration; public health - nursing; Russia - general commentary after two trips; and South America - life and customs, general commentary.
Principal correspondents in this collection include William Bailey, Marston Bates, Mark F. Boyd, Elizabeth W. Brackett, Henry P. Carr, Samuel T. Darling, Harry Fultz, H. M. Gillette, Hazel Hackett, John L. Hydrick, John H. Janney, Attilio Machiavello, Hugo Muench, Laura E. Richards, F. F. Russell, Wilbur A. Sawyer, D. H. Stevens, George K. Strode, Mary E. Tennant, Andrew J. Warren, Jean Martin White, and Abigail Sanborn Hackett.
Arrangement note
The Lewis W. Hackett collection is arranged in seven series:
Series 1 - Correspondence
Series 2 - Diaries
Series 3 - Speeches, Manuscripts, and Reprints
Series 4 - Reports
Series 5 - Malaria Data, Egypt
Series 6 - Miscellaneous
Series 1071 - Photographs, Negatives, and Slides
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Lewis W. Hackett were deposited with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in November 1971, December 1972, and March 1976, by Robert N. Hackett.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 22
Paris green; DDT (Insecticide); Political science; Epidemics; Diseases; Argentina; Buenos Aires (Argentina); Disease management -- Bolivia; Yellow fever; South America; Disease management -- Lurín River Valley (Peru); Public health administration; Russia; Epidemiology; Malaria; Insecticides; Tropical medicine; Public health nursing; National Institute of Hygiene. Guayaquil (Ecuador)
- Correspondence, 1875-1960; 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is divided into three subseries:
  Subseries 1 - General
  Subseries 2 - Buenos Aires Office
  Subseries 3 - Personal
  - Correspondence - General, 1902-1951, 1960; 1
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries contains unbound official and personal correspondence, both to and from Dr. Hackett. Most of the letters were exchanged with persons outside his family. This is not a complete file; the letters are extremely miscellaneous in nature and appear to have been kept for personal reasons and not to constitute a record. Although the series contains little official data, there is much that illustrates his talent for vivid description of the countries in which he worked and traveled. His humor and insight make these both entertaining and informative.
    This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1902 - October 19, 1951, 1960, and Undated, 1902-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - Buenos Aires Office, April 1941-September 1949; 2
    This subseries contains carbon copies of typewritten outgoing official correspondence. These were filed in string binders labeled "Reading File," and averaged two to three hundred letters each month. Many are in Spanish. The originals may exist in other files. The subjects are 1) routine internal Foundation business of limited interest, 2) International Health Division projects, especially in public health nursing and mosquito control, 3) fellowship recommendations and arrangements, and 4) some subjects of more than routine interest: e.g., annual estimates of funds needed for new projects. Important program developments are described in greater detail in Series 2 - Diaries.
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - April 5, 1941 - June 30, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - July 1, 1942 - September 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - October 1, 1943 - December 29, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - January 1, 1945 - December 31, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - January 2, 1946 - December 31, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 135)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 136)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 137)
    - January 13, 1947 - September 29, 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 138)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 144)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 145)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 147)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 148)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 149)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 150)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 151)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 152)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 153)
    - October 6, 1948 - September 30, 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - Correspondence - Personal, 1875-1948; 3
    This subseries contains unbound original personal correspondence, mostly from Dr. Hackett to his wife Hazel or his mother Abbie. There are some letters from Hazel to Dr. Hackett and to his mother. Letters to and from a few others, including his son Robert, will also be found in this subseries. The major topics covered are Dr. Hackett's duties and experiences during his internships at several Boston hospitals--these double as love letters during his engagement to Hazel and occur sometimes twice daily--and the unofficial details of his first assignment with the International Health Board in Panama. The letters begin to thin out in 1919, but there is interesting material about Italy scattered throughout the 1920s and an especially fascinating group of letters in July 1934, about his first trip through Russia.
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.01)
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.02)
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.03)
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.04)
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.05)
    - 1875 - June, 1911, 1875-1911 (Box 8A, Folder 154.06)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.07)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.08)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.09)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.1)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.11)
    - August, 1911 - June, 1912, 1911-1912 (Box 8B, Folder 154.12)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.13)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.14)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.15)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.16)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.17)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.18)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.19)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.2)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.21)
    - July, 1912 - December, 1919, 1912-1919 (Box 8C, Folder 154.22)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.23)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.24)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.25)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.26)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.27)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.28)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.29)
    - May, 1920 - December, 1948 & No Date Established, 1920-1948 (Box 8, Folder 154.3)
- Diaries, 1910-1962; 2
  This series is made up of official and personal diaries, both typewritten and longhand. The former are fully expanded, while the latter are usually brief notes. Some periods are missing or not covered. Most thoroughly documented are Hackett's early months in Italy in 1924 and his entire stay in Argentina from 1940 through September 1949. (All of the latter is duplicated in Hackett's diaries in the Rockefeller Foundation archives.) The years before 1924 are scarcely covered. The travel diaries are particularly interesting for human interest and local color.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Manuscript - Travel in Egypt, India, December 8, 1927-January 7, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - 1 Book - Honduras and Guatemala, 1916 (Box 9, Folder A)
  - 1 Book (Xerox Copy) - U. S., South America, Italy, 1910-1933 (Box 9, Folder B)
  - 1 Book - Italy, January 21-September 12, 1924 (Box 9, Folder C)
  - 1 Notebook - Travel in Egypt, India, December 3, 1927-January 3, 1928 (Box 9, Folder D)
    Preliminary notes for manuscript.
  - 1 Notebook - Travel in Ceylon, January 4-February 11, 1928 (Box 9, Folder E)
  - 1 Notebook - Travel in Sumatra, Siam, Malaya, Java, February 11-March 16, 1928 (Box 9, Folder F)
  - 1 Notebook - Travel in Java, Philippine Islands, March 16-April 7, 1928 (Box 9, Folder G)
  - Manuscript - Albania During Italian Occupation, March 31-April 10, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - 1 Book - Travel in Egypt, Italy, South America, Canada, U.S., May 1939-September 18, 1940 (Box 10, Folder A)
  - 1 Book - South America, September 6, 1940-December 16, 1942 (Box 10, Folder B)
  - 1 Book - South America, October 16, 1943-December 31, 1945 (Box 11, Folder A)
  - 1 Book - South America, January 1, 1946-December 31, 1947 (Box 11, Folder B)
  - Notes and Manuscripts - U.S. and Travel in Europe, September 26-December 31, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 157)